Guide to the James A. Kelly collection of Brooklyn firefighting records 1989.006
Brooklyn Historical Society
James A. Kelly collection of Brooklyn firefighting records
1825-1949
1850-1900
Center for Brooklyn History
1989.006
195 Linear Feet in 201 ledgers, 18 record cartons, 11 manuscript boxes, and 2 flat boxes
The collection represents a portion of the material generated by several Brooklyn and Kings County volunteer fire companies and by related local, county, state, and national organizations, between 1825 and 1949. The bulk of the material spans the time period between 1850 and 1900.
Related Archival Materials note
For additional primary materials pertaining to firefighting in Brooklyn, see also:
Brooklyn Volunteer Fire Department, Atlantic Hose Company No.1 manuscript (1973.215)
Village of Brooklyn Fire Department member lists and minutes (1973.275)
Board of Trustees of the Brooklyn Fire Department meeting minutes (1977.080)
Williamsburgh fire wardens minute book (1977.158)
Mrs. M.G. Spooner resolution (1978.017)
Flatbush Fire Company records (1978.019)
New York City fire fighters list (1978.032)
Durham family papers (1985.021)
Brooklyn Fire Department journals (1985.024)
Brooklyn Fire Department pamphlets (1985.070)
Brooklyn Fire Department payroll records (1985.077)
Brooklyn Fire Department ephemera (1985.087)
Brooklyn Fire Department ledgers (1990.004)
Brooklyn Firemen's Ball records (1992.017)
Brooklyn Fire Department discharge (1992.018)
Brooklyn Engine 141 collection (2004.002)
Brooklyn, N.Y., Department of Law, Corporation Counsel records (2013.015)
City of New York Fire Department 31st Battalion fire record journal (2015.003)
Teunis G. Bergen and Bergen family collection (ARC.006)
Brooklyn City Armory cornerstone collection (ARC.024)
BHS also holds the James A. Kelly papers (1977.342)
Conditions Governing Access
Open to users without restrictions.
Inventory note
Please note that box numbers followed by a "w" indicate that the item is an individual ledger that has been wrapped for preservation purposes.
Scope and Contents
The collection represents a portion of the material generated by several Brooklyn and Kings County volunteer fire companies and by related local, county, state, and national organizations, between 1825 and 1949. The bulk of the material spans the time period between 1850 and 1900.
Included in the collection are: appointments, bids, bonds, broadsides, certificates, circulars, clippings, communications, contracts, correspondence, deeds, drawings, estimates, ledgers, letters, minutes, notices, orders, petitions, receipts, recommendations, regulations, reports, requests, resolutions, rolls, rosters, speeches, and telegrams. It also includes related photographs and objects.
Other Finding Aids
Previous versions of this finding aid are available in the collection's accession file. Please consult library staff for more information.
Historical note
The first record of organized firefighting in Brooklyn dates from 1772, when six local men were recruited to combat fires near "the Ferry," a settlement having risen around the ferry landing at the foot of present day Fulton Street. A company of volunteers, consisting of seven men chosen at the town meeting, was formed in 1785. Beginning in 1788, those Brooklyn firemen who had performed the prescribed length of service were exempted from jury duty and militia service, which swelled the ranks of the volunteers. Upon the incorporation of the Village of Brooklyn in 1816, the Village Trustees were given "full authority to make their Fire Department what in their judgement it should be." The Trustees quickly established two new companies, increasing the total roll to ninety five men. The Trustees also established the offices of four fire wardens, elected for the first time in 1817.
The three volunteer companies of what became known as the Western District, were represented by a Chief Engineer, who was nominated and directly elected by the firemen until 1827, when the election was delegated to the foremen of the respective companies. The selection process returned to the firemen themselves in 1839 with the re-institution of direct elections, which process usually reflected local, regional, and national politics as well as ethno-cultural affinities and social rank. The Chief Engineer reported to the Trustees of the Village of Brooklyn and, after the incorporation of the City of Brooklyn in 1834, to the Common Council of Brooklyn. The institution of the "Annual Report of the Chief Engineer to the Mayor and Common Council" was inaugurated in 1828.
The Village of Williamsburgh organized a firefighting force and purchased two engines for two companies, "Washington" and "Protection Engine" in 1834. In 1844, a third company was added, "Good Interest." The Williamsburgh Fire Department included seventeen companies by 1854, at which time the City of Williamsburgh (chartered 1851) consolidated with the city of Brooklyn. Upon consolidation, the Williamsburgh Fire Department's name was changed to the Fire Department of the Eastern District.
By the mid-nineteenth century, the administrative portion of the Brooklyn Fire Department had grown to include: a Board of Representatives, made up of a fireman from each company; a Board of Trustees, which supervised the allocation and disposal of funds generated by dues and other benefits; various standing committees; a Board of Fire Commissioners; a Board of Officers composed of the Chief Engineer, Assistant Engineers, and the Foreman of each company; the Board of Fire Wardens; and, the Exempt Firemen's Association. Each fire company "chose its own members, generally from among near neighbors, friends, and relatives, and thus directly reflected the social composition of the several wards." Close proximity between the firehouse and residence was necessary to ensure maximum efficiency and prompt response.
Living and working together in often dangerous conditions bound the men into a brotherhood, and made each man the judge of his mates' strength, willingness, and agility. These were qualities needed to pull an engine through uneven, garbage-strewn streets, to dodge a crumbling fiery wall, or to assert and defend the company's honor against a variety of challenges.
The firehouses functioned as neighborhood clubhouses of sorts, attracted hangers-on who ran with the official volunteers, and provided a meeting place for the members of the firefighting fraternity. Records indicate that membership in a volunteer company became an important component of social identity.
Competition between individual companies was strong and frequently resulted in violence both at the scene of a fire and en route. Companies often competed to be first at a blaze and tried to eclipse each other's apparatus in pumping power. Great physical endurance was required to pull the engines through cobblestoned and unpaved streets in all weather and to pump water from the East River prior to the formation of the Nassau Water Company, which began pumping Ridgewood (Long Island) Reservoir water into Brooklyn in 1858.
The fraternal aspects of the brotherhood of volunteer firemen extended beyond the local company. Volunteer firemen administered relief in the form of sick benefits, pensions, and widows' and orphans' stipends, and mortgages and loans became available through the Firemen's Fund. Capital was generated by fundraising activities such as balls and musical entertainments, as well as through the collection of dues and fines.
As the population of Brooklyn grew rapidly during the 1840s and 1850s, as a result of both in-migration and large waves of Irish and German immigrants, the size and density of the growing city began to show the inadequacies of a volunteer force of autonomous companies that were unable to fight fires effectively. Fire Department officials petitioned the Mayor and Common Council for funds to establish new firehouses as well as to maintain and purchase equipment and supplies. The "Annual Report of the Chief Engineer, Western District" for 1863 indicated the contemporary size of the Fire Department:
"The working force of the Department, at the present time consists of eight Engineers, eleven hundred and twenty two members of Engine Companies, four hundred and ten Hose Companies. And one hundred and ninety five members of Hook and Ladder Companies, making a total of seventeen hundred and twenty seven men. The Department is divided into fourteen hand engines, fifteen hose carriages, and five hook and ladder trucks, all of which are doing duty."
The volunteer status of firemen was sharply challenged in the mid-nineteenth century as firefighting effectiveness diminished in the rapidly urbanizing city. The first bill to establish a paid Fire Department in Brooklyn was introduced and defeated in 1858, but the capability of the volunteer Fire Department was further contested as Brooklyn became an industrial center during the Civil War. The City of Brooklyn replaced cisterns with hydrants that dispensed a steady and predictable water supply, while technological advances in the form of horse drawn steam pumping engines threatened volunteer companies that pulled their pumpers through the streets by hand, sometimes to the risk of life and limb to themselves and passersby. The fire brigades' autonomy, but not their identity, was summarily altered by "An Act to Create a Metropolitan Fire District" which in 1865, merged the Fire Departments of the City of New York and the Eastern and Western Districts of the City of Brooklyn under the jurisdiction of Metropolitan Fire Commissioners appointed by the governor.
The companies remained volunteer in nature, but the consolidation produced renewed demands for a paid firefighting force for the city. "An Act to Reorganize the Fire Department of the City of Brooklyn" received approval in 1869, which moved governance of the fire department from New York State to New York City elected and appointed officials. The Mayor, the Comptroller, and the Street Commissioner acquired authority over the four Commissioners of the Fire Department. The Trustees of the Widows and Orphans Fund of the Fire Department reported to the Common Council of the City of Brooklyn, while annual appropriations for Fire Department expenses were relegated to the King's County Board of Supervisors. The bill also suggested that the new Fire Commissioners select members of the paid department from among exempt firemen, who had served a full term in the Volunteer Department.
The cities of Brooklyn and Williamsburg converted from volunteer brigades to a paid fire department by 1870. Thereafter the transition from a volunteer to a paid firefighting force took place upon the annexation of individual towns into the city of Brooklyn as follow: New Lots, 1886; Flatbush, 1894; Gravesend, 1894; New Utrecht, 1894; and Flatlands, 1896. Brooklyn became a borough of New York City in January 1898.
After the transition from a volunteer to a salaried Fire Department in Brooklyn and the annexed towns, Veteran Volunteer Associations served as surrogates for the vanished volunteer firehouses and maintained their traditional identities and affinities. In addition, ex-volunteers were eligible for membership in state and national firefighting organizations that accepted both professional firefighters and volunteers. The "vamps" of the old department perpetuated the fraternal aspects of the volunteer firehouses through these associations and organizations, maintaining the disbursements of benefits and pensions virtually as long as there were eligible veterans or their beneficiaries to receive such.
Sources:
Belknap, Rufus R. The Fireman's Almanac and Reference Book for the Year 1860, containing in addition to the calendar a memorandum. New York: H. Dexter & Co., 1860.
Brooklyn Fire Department. Our Firemen. Brooklyn, N.Y., 1892.
Brooklyn Fire Department. Report of the Special Commission in Matters of Reorganizing the Fire Department of the City of Brooklyn. New York: Wynkoop, Hallenbeck and Thomas, 1861.
Kernan, J. Frank. Reminiscences of the Old Fire Laddies and Volunteer Fire Departments of New York and Brooklyn: together with a complete history of the paid departments of both cities. New York: M. Crane, 1885.
Limpus, Lowell M. History of the New York Fire Department. New York: E.P. Dutton, 1940.
New York Fire Department. Centennial Issue: Fire Department, 1865-1965. New York, c. 1965.
O'Reilly, Joseph John Edward. How to Become a Fireman; with all the information relative to civil service requirements, examinations, and the school of instruction. New York: The Chief Publishing Co., c.1903.
Ordinances of the Village of Williamsburgh related to firemen and the Fire Department. Williamsburgh, N.Y.: published by order of the Board of Trustees, 1850.
Pettit, Marilyn. The Brooklyn Volunteer Fire Department, 1836-70. New York University, 1981, unpublished.
Sprague, William E. Old Times. The early days of the Brooklyn Fire Department: the formation of the first fire company, the original machine, and how it was worked, primitive implements for battling with the flames – "that horrid bell". Bay Ridge, Long Island: James H. Barr, Job printer, 1882.
Stryker-Rodda, Harriet. Outline of the History of Firefighting on Long Island. Long Island Historical Society, 1955.
Why New York City should have a paid Fire Department. New York: C.S. Wescott & Co., Printers, 1865.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of St. Francis College, 1989.
Custodial History
The bulk of the collection was transferred to Brooklyn Historical Society (BHS) from the James A. Kelly Institute for Local Historical Studies of St. Francis College in Brooklyn in August 1989. Other portions of the Kelly Institute's collections were transferred to Brooklyn College Library Special Collections and to the Municipal Archives of the City of New York, and a portion of the present collection was already in the custody of BHS.
The collection was originally acquired through the efforts of James A. Kelly, Deputy County Clerk of King's County from 1944 to 1971, who removed a large volume of Brooklyn materials in 1956 from Brooklyn Borough Hall and the Brooklyn Municipal Building on Joralemon Street to St. Francis College when they were threatened with destruction. Included in the archives were municipal records of the City of Brooklyn from 1645 through 1898, as well as records of the six original towns of Kings County. Kelly was designated the first official historian of the borough of Brooklyn during this time.
The collection was first surveyed by Robert Sink (Brooklyn Rediscovery project) in the 1970s.
Arrangement
The collection is organized into twelve series:
Series 1: Brooklyn Volunteer Fire Department, Western District
Series 2: Brooklyn Volunteer Fire Department, Eastern District
Series 3: Brooklyn Volunteer Fire Department, Eastern and Western Districts
Series 4: Flatbush Volunteer Fire Department
Series 5: Gravesend Volunteer Fire Department
Series 6: New Lots Volunteer Fire Department
Series 7: State and National Firefighting Associations
Series 8: Photographs
Series 9: Scrapbooks
Series 10: Printed Material
Series 11: Artifacts and works on paper
Series 12: Miscellaneous and unidentified
Separated Materials
116 artifacts were separated to the Museum collection. Please see PastPerfect records for M1989.44 for more information.
Artifacts (object genre); Broadsides (notices); Brooklyn (New York, N.Y.); Certificates; Coney Island (New York, N.Y.); Correspondence; Ephemera; Financial records; Fire departments |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Fire fighters |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Flatbush (New York, N.Y.); Flatlands (New York, N.Y.); Gravesend (New York, N.Y.); Insurance records; Ledgers (account books); Minutes; New Lots (New York, N.Y.); Periodicals; Photographs; Receipts (financial records); Reports; Scrapbooks; Sheepshead Bay (New York, N.Y.); Volunteer fire companies |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Williamsburg (New York, N.Y.)
- Series 1: Brooklyn Volunteer Fire Department, Western District, 1825-1949
  Arrangement
  Organized into two sub-series:
  Sub-series 1.1: Ledgers
  Sub-series 1.2: Documents
  Scope and Contents
  The series contains material derived from the original Village and City of Brooklyn, referred to as the Western District of the Brooklyn Fire Department. Items include minute and account books, pension rolls, Board resolutions, mutual aid certificates, materials regarding the Brooklyn Volunteer Firemen's Association, and roll books dating from 1825 to 1949. Of special note in this series is Ledger 36, which contains clippings regarding inter-company fighting while racing to the scene of a fire, and ensuing disciplinary action. Ledger 38 lists the returns by company for the election of Chief Engineer of the Western District, 1855-1865. Ledger 91 lists benefits payments by the Committee on Relief Fund by name, date, and ward for 1861. Also of note are the committee reports to the Board of Trustees of the Western District, many of which pertain to the Widows and Orphans Fund. The role of the benefits and economic need of women in the volunteer fire department organization is illustrated in these documents.
  - Sub-series 1.1: Ledgers, 1825-1934
    Arranged chronologically, with groups of specific engine company ledgers placed at the end of the series.
    - Proceedings of the Board of Trustees, Fire Department (minutes) (ledger 75), 1825-1828 (Box 18)
    - Treasurer Brooklyn Fire Department (accounts) (ledger 76), 1837-1858 (Box 18)
    - Firemen's Register (roll) (ledger 9), 1852-1864 (Box 25w)
    - Record Book of Niagara Engine Company No. 8, Brooklyn, L.I. (record book) (ledger 77), 1853-1865 (Box 16)
    - Minutes and Ledger Montauk Hose Company No. 4 (minutes and dues accounts) (ledger 55), 1853-1859 (Box 13)
    - Roll book, Montauk Engine Company No. 22 and Hose Company No. 4 (ledger 53), 1853-1861 (Box 13)
    - Dues accounts, unidentified Western District Company (ledger 57), 1854-1886 (Box 14)
    - Minutes, Trustees (ledger 34), 1854-1864 (Box 26w)
    - Chief Engineer's Returns (election results) (ledger 38), 1855-1865 (Box 27w)
    - Brooklyn Fire Items-Atlantic Hose Company No. 1 (scrapbook, photocopy Box 9) (ledger 145), 1855-1869 (Box 22)
    - Pensions and Claims (pension roll) (ledger 52), 1855-1871 (Box 13)
    - Engine Hose and Hook and Ladder Companies (ledger 30), 1856-1868 (Box 28w)
    - Roster Volunteer Fire Department, Brooklyn Western District, Engine Companies 21, 22, Hose Companies 1, 2, 3, 4, 5, 7, 8, 10, 11 and 14 Hook and Ladder Companies 1-5. (roll) (ledger 174), 1856-1869 (Box 23)
    - Badge Register Exempt 1-1200, Fire Companies, Western District (ledger 100), 1857-1868 (Box 19)
    - Discharge Certificates, book A (ledger 93), 1857-1869 (Box 18)
    - Report Book, Fire Commissioners, Western District (reports) (ledger 84), 1857-1869 (Box 18)
    - Minutes of Fire Commissioners (ledger 39), 1857-1869 (Box 29w)
    - Lafayette Hook and Ladder (roll) (ledger 12), 1857-1869 (Box 30w)
    - Badge Register (ledger 28), 1857-1869 (Box 31w)
    - Treasurer's Accounts, Fire Department, City Brooklyn (accounts) (ledger 19), 1858-1870 (Box 32w)
    - Montauk Engine Company No. 22, Minutes and Ledger (minutes) (ledger 42), 1859-1863 (Box 12)
    - Engine Companies 1 and 2 (roll) (ledger 170), 1859-1868 (Box 23)
    - Engine Companies 10, 11, 12, 13, 16, 17, 19, 20, 21, 22, Hook and Ladder Companies 1-6 (roll) (ledger 173), 1859-1869 (Box 23)
    - Attendance Book, Record of Arrears of 50% Duty (roll) (ledger 85), 1860-1868 (Box 18)
    - Roll book, Montauk Engine Company No. 22 (ledger 23), 1860-1868 (Box 33w)
    - Daily payments with names and amounts to each family paid by the Committee of the Relief Fund, Oct. 17- Dec. 4, 1861 (roll) (ledger 91) (Box 34w)
    - Roll Book, No. 2 (roll book of Montauk Engine Company No. 22) (ledger 36), 1862-1869 (Box 35w)
    - Scrapbook, Continental Engine Company No. 9 (photocopy Box 9) (ledger 123), 1863-1868 (Box 21)
    - Roster, Engine Companies 1-22 (ledger 3), 1863-1869 (Box 36w)
    - Roster, Hose Companies 1-17 and Hook and Ladder Companies 1-6 (roll book) (ledger 2), 1863-1869 (Box 37w)
    - Empire Engine Company No. 19, Minutes (ledger 78), 1863-1869 (Box 17)
    - Montauk Engine Company No. 22 (ledger 58), 1863-1869 (Box 14)
    - Roll book (roll book from unidentified Western District Company) (ledger 31), 1863-1868 (Box 38w)
    - Roll Book, unidentified Western District Company (ledger 33), 1864-1866 (Box 39w)
    - Minutes of the Board of Trustees, Brooklyn Fire Department (ledger 18), 1864-1871 (Box 40w)
    - Minutes, Committee on Claims and Relief (ledger 119), 1866-1870 (Box 21)
    - Roster, Volunteer Fire Department, Brooklyn, Western District, Engine Companies 1-17 and 19" (roll) (ledger 169), 1869 (Box 23)
    - Roll book, Engine Companies 1-22, Hose Companies 1-17 and Truck Companies 1-6 (ledger 1), circa 1869 (Box 41w)
    - Roll book of beneficiaries (ledger 162), 1872-1920 (Box 23)
    - Widows and Orphans Fund of the volunteer Fire Department of Brooklyn, Western District (roll) (ledger 186), 1873-1899 (Box 24)
    - Discharge Certificates Register, Book B (ledger 37), 1873-1911 (Box 42w)
    - Pensions, Widows and Orphans Fund (roll) (ledger 14), 1877-1882 (Box 43w)
    - Pensions, Brooklyn Fire Department, (roll) (ledger 8), 1882-1891 (Box 44w)
    - Brooklyn Volunteer Firemen's Association (minutes and roll) (ledger 166), 1883-1894 (Box 23)
    - Minutes, Volunteer Association Brooklyn, Western District (minutes) (ledger 59), 1884-1887 (Box 14)
    - Constitution, Volunteer Firemen's Association (includes roll) (ledger 83), 1885 (Box 18)
    - Volunteer Firemen's Association, Brooklyn, Western District (roll) (ledger 6), 1885-1905 (Box 45w)
    - Brooklyn Volunteer Firemen's Association, Western District (ledger 5), 1885-1923 (Box 46w)
    - Brooklyn Volunteer Firemen's Association (accounts) (ledger 62), 1886-1933 (Box 15)
    - Roster, Brooklyn Volunteer Fire Department (roll) (ledger 27), 1887 (Box 47w)
    - Association of Exempt Firemen, Brooklyn, Western District (dues accounts) (ledger 125), 1887-1897 (Box 21)
    - Minute Book No. 2, Brooklyn Volunteer Firemen's Association (minutes) (ledger 11), circa 1880-1891 (Box 48w)
    - Brooklyn Volunteer Firemen's Association, Western District (roll) (ledger 22), 1890-1912 (Box 49w)
    - Fines (account book of fines) (ledger 152), 1893-1900 (Box 22)
    - Roll book and dues accounts, Western District (ledger 48), 1897-1903 (Box 50w)
    - Franklin (Engine Company No. 3- accounts) (ledger 88), 1898-1906 (Box 16)
    - Receipts for Pensions (roll) (ledger 15), 1901-1911 (Box 51w)
    - Brooklyn Volunteer Firemen's Association (minutes) (ledger 24), 1903-1923 (Box 52w)
    - Dues accounts and roll, Western District (ledger 49), 1903-1923 (Box 53w)
    - Check Stubs 300-599, Brooklyn Volunteer Firemen's Association (ledger 107), 1912-1925 (Box 19)
    - Brooklyn Volunteer Firemen's Association, John B. Byrne, Treasurer (bank book) (ledger 177), 1913-1930 (Box 24)
    - Roll of members and dues accounts, Brooklyn Volunteer Firemen's Association (ledger 179), 1915-1920 (Box 24)
    - Roll, widowed beneficiaries (ledger 168), 1916-1917 (Box 23)
    - Brooklyn Volunteer Firemen's Association (dues accounts) (ledger 178), 1916-1922 (Box 24)
    - Dues accounts, Brooklyn Volunteer Firemen's Association (ledger 181), 1923 (Box 24)
    - Minutes of the Brooklyn Volunteer Exempt Firemen's Association (minutes) (ledger 86), 1923-1931 (Box 18)
    - Minute Book, Brooklyn Volunteer Firemen's Association (minutes) (ledger 87), 1923-1931 (Box 16)
    - Check book, Brooklyn Volunteer Firemen's Association (ledger 46), 1925-1930 (Box 12)
    - Engine Company 105 (205), Fire Record, 1902-1904 (Box 69w)
    - Engine Company 105 (205), Fire Record, 1904-1911 (Box 226)